Cigar Makers International Union Records on Microfilm 5724 mf
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cigar Makers International Union Records on Microfilm
1856-1974
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Cigar Makers International Union
5724 mf
0.67 cubic feet
6 microfilm reels
Records (documents), microfilm.
Microfilm copy of Cigar Makers' International Union of America records including, agreements, financial statements and membership ledgers
5698073
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, September 26, 2012
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 28, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The Journeymen Cigar Makers' International Union of America (CMIU) was a labor union established in 1864 that represented workers in the cigar industry. The CMIU was part of the American Federation of Labor from 1887 until its merger in 1974.
The first local Cigar Makers' Union was founded in Baltimore, Maryland in 1851. In 1863 came the first effort to establish a nationa union of cigar makers, bringing delegates from New York, Philadelphia, Newark, Cleveland, New Haven, Boston and Detroit. The first national union formed was called the National Union of Cigar Makers of America, but, eventually changed its name to the Journeymen Cigar Markers' International Union (CMIU) in 1867.
The CMIU was instrumental in the formation of the Federation of Organized Trades and Labor Unions in 1881, which later evolved into the American Federation of Labor (AF of L). In 1882 the CMIU split in two over the question of political endorsements, the second union formed was known as the Cigarmakers' Progressive Union of America. The unions reunited in 1886. The final merger for the CMIU was in 1974 when the union merged into the Retail, Wholesale and Department Store Union.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5211: Labor Leader Biographies 5488 C: BRAC Additional Records 5724 mf: Cigar Makers International Union Records on Microfilm 6043 MB: Union Memorabilia Collection 6046: Archives Union File (AUF) 6178/010: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 10) 6178/022 mf: BLS Collection of Collective Bargaining Agreements (Part 22) on Microfilm
Arrangement
Series I: Administration
Series II: Locals
Series III: Financial Records
Sub-Series 1: Correspondence Sub-Series 2: Ledgers & Financial Statements
Cigar makers; Cigar industry; Cassaro, Frank; Cigar Makers' International Union of America
5698073
- Series I: Administration
  - Canadian Labor Congress, 1945-1974; 1 (Reel 1)
  - Frank Cassaro, 1937-1939; 2 (Reel 1)
    Scope and Contents
    1937 - June 1939
  - Frank Cassaro, 1939-1956; 3 (Reel 1)
    July 1939 - 1956
  - Frank Cassaro Field Reports, 1957-1953; 4 (Reel 1)
  - Frank Cassaro r and p, 5 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Machine, 1927-1937; 6 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Cooperative Association, 1931-1950; 7 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Manufacturers Code, 8 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Manufacturers Assn. of Tampa, 1960; 9 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Progressive Union:, 10 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Progressive Union: Executive Minutes, 1886; 11 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Progressive Union: Minutes, 1884-1889; 12 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Progressive Union: Minutes, joint conference with CMIUA, 1886; 13 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Progressive Union: Protocol, 1886; 14 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Tax, 1931-1938; 15 (Reel 1)
  - Cigar Makers Progressive Union, 1885; 16 (Reel 1)
  - Civil Rights, 1964; 1 (Reel 2)
  - Clippings, 2 (Reel 2)
  - Committee on Political Education, 1949-1973; 3 (Reel 2)
  - Constitutional Amendments, 1949; 4 (Reel 2)
  - Correspondence, 1931-1941; 5 (Reel 2)
  - Correspondence, 1942-1974; 6 (Reel 2)
  - Elmina Crews - field reports, 1957-1960; 7 (Reel 2)
  - Cuban Cigars, 1938; 8 (Reel 2)
  - Albert D'Arpa, 1956-1972; 9 (Reel 2)
  - Josephine de la Grana - field reports, 1936; 10 (Reel 2)
  - Otto Dehn, 1957; 11 (Reel 2)
  - Democrats for Humphrey, 1968; 12 (Reel 2)
  - Frances Perkins, Thomas Finn, 13 (Reel 2)
  - Frances Perkins, Thomas Finn r and p, 14 (Reel 2)
  - Frances Perkins, Thomas Finn Wage and Hour Div. reports, 1939; 15 (Reel 2)
- Series II: Locals
  - Local 27, Toronto Canada, 1927-1926; 1 (Reel 3)
  - Local 27, Toronto Canada, 1938-1968; 2 (Reel 3)
  - Local 27, Toronto Canada Agreements, 1945-1954; 3 (Reel 3)
  - Local 27, Toronto Canada Minutes, 1864-1871; 4 (Reel 3)
  - Local 28, Westfield, Mass., 1930-1968; 5 (Reel 3)
  - Local 32, Louisville, Ky., 1928-1950; 6 (Reel 3)
  - Local 32, Louisville, Ky., 1952-1963; 7 (Reel 3)
  - Local 33, 1945; 8 (Reel 3)
  - Local 34, Chippewa Falls, Wis., 1931; 9 (Reel 3)
  - Local 37, Fort Wayne, Ind., 1944; 10 (Reel 3)
  - Local 38, Springfield, Il., 1945; 11 (Reel 3)
  - Local 39, New Haven, Conn., 1927-1970; 12 (Reel 3)
  - Local 39, New Haven, Conn. Agreements, 1942-1972; 13 (Reel 3)
  - Local 42, Hartford, Conn. - Agreements, 1937-1942; 14 (Reel 3)
  - Local 44, St. Louis, Mo., 1926-1949; 15 (Reel 3)
  - Local 44, St. Louis, Mo, 1950-1973; 16 (Reel 3)
  - Local 47, Quincy, Il. - Agreements, 1945; 17 (Reel 3)
  - Local 49, Springfield, Mass., 1937-1944; 18 (Reel 3)
  - Local 51, Holyoke, Mass., 1945; 19 (Reel 3)
  - Local 54, Evansville, Ind., 1945; 20 (Reel 3)
  - Local 53, New Orleans, La., 1940; 21 (Reel 3)
  - Local 64, Lebanon, Pa., 1919; 22 (Reel 3)
  - Local 77, Minneapolis, Minn., 1945; 23 (Reel 3)
  - Local 83, Nashville, Tenn., 1945; 24 (Reel 3)
  - Local 85, Poughkeepsie, NY, 1937-1959; 25 (Reel 3)
  - Local 86, Jacksonville, Fla., 1940-1974; 26 (Reel 3)
  - Local 395, Waterbury, Conn., 1933-1951; 1 (Reel 4)
  - Local 396, Northampton, Mass., 1945; 2 (Reel 4)
  - Local 398, Stamford, Conn., 1945; 3 (Reel 4)
  - Local 404, 1944; 4 (Reel 4)
  - Local 405, Montgomery, Ala., 1928; 5 (Reel 4)
  - Local 420, Portland, Maine, 1934-1935; 6 (Reel 4)
  - Local 431, 1945; 7 (Reel 4)
  - Local 457, Benton Harbor, Mich., 1952-1957; 8 (Reel 4)
  - Local 460, San Juan, Puerto Rico, 1927-1972; 9 (Reel 4)
  - Local 462, Tampa, Fla., 1936-1972; 10 (Reel 4)
  - Local 468, Albion, Mich., 1920-1945; 11 (Reel 4)
  - Local 471+, Tampa, Fla., 1937-1971; 12 (Reel 4)
  - Local 476, Pontiac, Il., 1927-1928; 13 (Reel 4)
  - Local 482, Wasau, Wis., 1945-1950; 14 (Reel 4)
  - Local 484, Meriden, Conn., 1953-1956; 15 (Reel 4)
  - Local 488, Middletown, NY, 1928; 16 (Reel 4)
  - Local 493, Tampa, Fla., 1934-1960; 17 (Reel 4)
  - Local 494, Tampa, Fla., 1939-1973; 18 (Reel 4)
  - Local 495, Tampa, Fla., 1938-1947; 19 (Reel 4)
  - Local 500, Tampa, Fla., 1927-1973; 20 (Reel 4)
  - Local 501, Wheeling, W.V.., 1937; 21 (Reel 4)
  - Local 502, Tampa, Fla., 1942-1973; 22 (Reel 4)
  - Local 516, Wheeling, W. V.., 1927-1928; 23 (Reel 4)
  - Local 520, Manchester, N.H., 1928; 24 (Reel 4)
  - Local 526, Philadelphia, Pa., 1936; 25 (Reel 4)
  - Allied Tobacco Trades Council, 1934-1935; 26 (Reel 4)
  - Cigar Manufacturers Assn., Agreement, 1957; 27 (Reel 4)
  - Webster-Eisenlohr, Inc., 1937; 28 (Reel 4)
  - Miscellaneous, 29 (Reel 4)
  - Local 14, Agreements, 1942-1951; 30 (Reel 4)
  - Local 25, Agreements, 1947-1960; 31 (Reel 4)
  - Local 27, Agreements, 1856-1874; 32 (Reel 4)
  - Local 39, Agreements and Minutes, 1914-1952; 33 (Reel 4)
  - Locals 86, 119, Agreements, 1949-1960; 34 (Reel 4)
  - Locals 99, 100, Agreements, 1950-1960; 35 (Reel 4)
  - Locals 99, 100, 501, Agreements, 1941-1973; 36 (Reel 4)
  - Local 100, Wheeling, W.V.., Agreements, 1964-1969; 37 (Reel 4)
  - Local 104, Agreements, 1938-1940; 38 (Reel 4)
  - Local 136, Agreements, 1950-1968; 39 (Reel 4)
  - Locals 163, 178, Agreements, 1940-1957; 40 (Reel 4)
  - Local 225, Agreement, 1951-1956; 41 (Reel 4)
  - Local 242, Agreement, 1949-1972; 42 (Reel 4)
  - Local 255, Agreement, 1953; 43 (Reel 4)
  - Local 258, Agreement, 1946; 44 (Reel 4)
  - Local 295, Agreement, 1967-1973; 45 (Reel 4)
  - Local 383, 384, Agreement, 1950; 46 (Reel 4)
  - Agreement Summary, 1940-1945; 47 (Reel 4)
  - Cigar Manufacturers Assn., Agreements, 1933-1961; 48 (Reel 4)
  - Jose Escalenta & Co., Agreement, 1939; 49 (Reel 4)
  - General Cigar Co., Agreement, 1942; 50 (Reel 4)
  - Standard Cigar Co., 1956; 51 (Reel 4)
  - M. Trelles & Co., Agreement, 1939; 52 (Reel 4)
- Series III: Financial Records
  - Sub-Series 1: Correspondence
    - Union Labor Life Insurance, 1958-1972; 1 (Reel 5)
    - Union Labor Life Insurance, Reports, 2 (Reel 5)
    - Welfare and Pension Reports, 1959-1960; 3 (Reel 5)
    - D.C. Unemployment Compensation, 1936-1939; 4 (Reel 5)
    - Defaulters, 1887-1907; 5 (Reel 5)
    - Deficiency Statement, 1938; 6 (Reel 5)
    - Employers Federal Tax Report, 1938-1955; 7 (Reel 5)
    - Financial Statements, 1928-1955; 8 (Reel 5)
    - Financial Report, 1882-1911; 9 (Reel 5)
    - Insurance, 1927-1932; 10 (Reel 5)
    - Membership Statement, 1937-1944; 11 (Reel 5)
    - Percentage Accounts, 1926-1927; 12 (Reel 5)
    - Strike Report, 1 (Reel 6)
  - Sub-Series 2: Ledgers & Financial Statements
    - Local 2, Buffalo, NY, Dues Book, 1860-1865; 2 (Reel 6)
    - Local 25,Milwaukee, Wis., Dues Book, 1958-1966; 3 (Reel 6)
    - Local 25, Financial Statements, 1946-1948; 4 (Reel 6)
    - Local 25, Ledger, 1949-1966; 5 (Reel 6)
    - Local 39, New Haven, Conn., Ledger, 1961-1969; 6 (Reel 6)
    - Local 86, Jacksonville, Fla, Financial Statement, 1945; 7 (Reel 6)
    - Local 116, Huntington, W.Va., Financial Statement, 1950; 8 (Reel 6)
    - Local 110, Washington, DC, Financial Statements, 1958-1962; 9 (Reel 6)
    - Local 119, Jacksonville, Fla., Fin. Statements, 1942-1945; 10 (Reel 6)
    - Local 130, Saginaw, Mich., Financial Statements, 1927; 11 (Reel 6)
    - Local 151, Havana, Cuba, Financial Statement, 1927; 12 (Reel 6)
    - Local 163, Ledger, 1961-1969; 13 (Reel 6)
    - Local 178, Ledger, 1947-1969; 14 (Reel 6)
    - Local 242, Ledger, 1969-1971; 15 (Reel 6)
    - Local 462, Financial Statement, 1960; 16 (Reel 6)
    - Individual Membership Ledger, 1934-1959; 17 (Reel 6)
    - Label Ledger, 1934-1959; 18 (Reel 6)
    - Local 92, Ledger, 1941-1954; 19 (Reel 6)
    - Local 110, Membership Ledger, 1928-1963; 20 (Reel 6)
    - Local 110, Ledger, 1928-1962; 21 (Reel 6)
    - Strike Benefit Record, 1927-1951; 22 (Reel 6)
    - Strike Benefits, 23 (Reel 6)
    - Locals Ledger, 1927; 24 (Reel 6)
    - Analysis Ledgers, 1928-1954; 25 (Reel 6)
      1928-1937; 1938-1954
    - Locals Financial Reports, 1955-1961; 26 (Reel 6)